<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Immunology | Arin Wongprommoon</title>
    <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/tag/immunology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/tag/immunology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Immunology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Immunology</title>
      <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/tag/immunology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Melittin Induced G1 Cell Cycle Arrest and Apoptosis in Chago-K1 Human Bronchogenic Carcinoma Cells and Inhibited the Differentiation of THP-1 Cells into Tumour-Associated Macrophages</title>
      <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/tipgomutmelittininducedg12018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/tipgomutmelittininducedg12018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;lay-summary&#34;&gt;Lay summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lung cancers are resistant to many drugs. Bee venom contains a protein called melittin. We want to know if it kills lung cancer cells and stops macrophages &amp;ndash; a type of white blood cell &amp;ndash; from changing cell type. Macrophages are important as it changes behaviour in lung cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested melittin on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how well it kills lung cancer cells,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how well it stops lung cancer cells from dividing,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how it affects macrophages moving and changing cell type,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how it affects the cancer producing a chemical that makes blood vessels grow towards it, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how it affects the levels of RNAs that show the activity of lung cancer cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that melittin does indeed kill cancer cells and stop them from dividing, if we use a particular concentration. Melittin also stops macrophages from changing cell type. However, melittin does not change how well the cancer tells the body to make new blood vessels. We also saw how melittin change how lung cancer cells produce RNAs that instruct processes in the cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we think doctors can use melittin to treat lung cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My role&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I performed some experiments. I added melittin in various concentrations to see which concentration kills the lung cancer cells. This work became figure 5 in the paper. I also performed RT-qPCR to detect RNAs &amp;ndash; this is the same technique people use to perform PCR tests to detect COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also gave feedback on the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
