<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Metabolic modelling | Arin Wongprommoon</title>
    <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/tag/metabolic-modelling/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/tag/metabolic-modelling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Metabolic modelling</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Metabolic modelling</title>
      <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/tag/metabolic-modelling/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-cell metabolic oscillations are pervasive and may alleviate a proteome constraint</title>
      <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/wongprommoonsinglecellmetabolicoscillations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/wongprommoonsinglecellmetabolicoscillations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;lay-summary&#34;&gt;Lay summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biological rhythms are essential to controlling the function of living organisms. One such example is the metabolic cycle in budding yeast, which consists of cycling levels of metabolites, RNA transcripts, and oxygen consumption over time. Most studies on this cycle have been performed with chemostats, in batch-cultures. Though there are more recent studies that image cells individually, it is unclear how to reconcile finding from the two types of experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this preprint, we show that pH levels in yeast cells also oscillate along with flavin redox state. These oscillations are present across a greater range of nutrient conditions and yeast mutants than observed before, including conditions in which such oscillations were disrupted in chemostats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explain why these oscillations are so prevalent, we used flux balance analysis &amp;ndash; a linear programming-based mathematical method to model biochemical reaction networks. With this tool, we show that, if a cell with a finite level of amino acids makes its biological building blocks (proteins, carbohydrates, lipids, etc.) in sequence, it saves time on growth. Thus, This sequence of synthesis may explain the metabolic oscillations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My role&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work represents a fusion of multiple disciplines and tools. To observe the cells, I needed to learn how to use a microfluidics device with so many moving parts. Monitoring cell division was made possible by using CRISPR-Cas9 to engineer a genetic insertion (and I learnt how to do this while social distancing during the COVID-19 pandemic). The time-lapse microscope produces a lot of images, so the research group needed to develop &lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/aliby/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;new software to process them&lt;/a&gt; and I wrote functions to perform time-series analysis. Finally, we used a tool from metabolic engineering, flux balance analysis, to help formulate a theoretical explanation of our observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also co-wrote the initial draft of the manuscript, and documented the datasets and code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing the accuracy of genome-scale metabolic models with kinetic information</title>
      <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/lazaroenhancingaccuracygenomescale2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/lazaroenhancingaccuracygenomescale2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;lay-summary&#34;&gt;Lay summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common way to simulate metabolism in an organism is by metabolic models &amp;ndash; mathematical equations that describe the dynamics of chemical reactions. Genome-scale constraint-based metabolic models account for most reactions that can occur in a cell and can be used to predict how much a genetically engineered microbe can produce an industrially relevant compound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a common method to simulate constraint-based metabolic models forces cellular reactions to either be optimised only for growth or only for production of the new compound &amp;ndash; neither of which is realistic. We solve this problem for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; producing citramalate by using information from another type of metabolic model to constrain the reaction fluxes in the base constraint-based model for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Project</title>
      <link>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/project/phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/project/phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My PhD project was conducted under the joint supervision of &lt;a href=&#34;https://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/doyarzun/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Diego Oyarzún&lt;/a&gt; (computational) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://swainlab.bio.ed.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof Peter Swain&lt;/a&gt; (laboratory &amp;amp; computational), at the University of Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project examined the metabolic cycle in budding yeast. This yeast metabolic cycle is defined by levels of metabolites in the cell increasing and decreasing in regular cycles, which are linked to cell division. Changing feeding conditions for the yeast cells or removing genes from the yeast genome that are responsible for metabolic processes affect the speed of these metabolic cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not a lot of people study this cycle. Those who do study them in chemostats &amp;ndash; essentially, large liquid cultures of many cells &amp;ndash; so it is difficult to see whether individual cells behave differently. This is why I used microfluidics to separate the cells. Microfluidics refers to an experimental system that moves around small amounts of liquids &amp;ndash; in my case, I used microfluidics to move cells from cultures, trap &amp;amp; separate them, then add or remove nutrients over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project had three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find out ways to analyse the thousands of oscillatory time series I produced.&lt;/em&gt; Microfluidics is nice because I got data from many cells. But then I had to clean, process, and categorise this data. I also found out that commonly-used computational methods to compute the periodicity of data, such as the Fourier transform, did not work so well with the noisy biological data I have. My aim was then to find alternative methods, and to combine them with other data-processing steps in a data analysis pipeline. In &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/arinwongprommoon/phd-synthetic-oscillations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this code repository&lt;/a&gt;, I investigated how noise in the data affect some analysis methods. And &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/arinwongprommoon/phd-time-series-char&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;using this repository&lt;/a&gt;, I used machine learning to tell apart oscillatory and non-oscillatory signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Show that the metabolic cycle occurs in a variety of cell conditions.&lt;/em&gt; My hypothesis here was that the metabolic cycle is something fundamental in the yeast cell, therefore I should be able to see oscillations in metabolite levels when the cells have certain genes removed, or are starved of nutrients. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.11.25.625147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;So far, so good.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/arinwongprommoon/wongprommoonSinglecellMetabolicOscillations2024&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Here is the code&lt;/a&gt; that I used to process the data I obtain from my microfluidics experiments to produce reports of the cells in each experiment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Use mathematical models of metabolism to explain why yeast cells have these metabolic cycles.&lt;/em&gt; More specifically, I answered the question: does it make sense for the cell to make different building blocks (carbohydrates, proteins, fats) at different times, and do these times fit with the periodicity of the metabolic cycle that I observed in experiments? To do this, I used a genome-scale metabolic model &amp;ndash; essentially, a list of chemical reactions that can happen in the yeast cell &amp;ndash; and solved linear programming problems to see how fast each reaction should be so that the cell grows as fast as possible. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/arinwongprommoon/phd-fba-temporal-biosynthesis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Here is the code&lt;/a&gt; that I used to solve these problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I was part of the team that developed &lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/aliby/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;aliby&lt;/a&gt;, a Python-based pipeline that Prof Peter Swain&amp;rsquo;s research group uses to analyse time-lapses of images of yeast cells taken from the microscopes in their microfluidics systems. This pipeline finds cells in the images (segmentation), keeps track of cells as they move through time (tracking), match new cells to the ones they divided from (lineage prediction), and creates time series for further processing. I used this software extensively in part 2 of my project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this was a valuable foray in collaborative software development. Of course, I sharpened my Python skills, but also DevOps: automated testing and deployment of software, managing software versions, maintaining servers for users, and making sure things don&amp;rsquo;t crash and burn. I learnt how to talk to other developers, project managers, and users (biologist and physicists) of varying programming or technical abilities. Naturally, I learnt to navigate lots and lots and lots of conflicts &amp;ndash; both merge conflicts and inevitable conflicts between ideas!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PhD work eventually led to a paper that showed that &lt;a href=&#34;https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/wongprommoonsinglecellmetabolicoscillations/&#34;&gt;single-cell metabolic oscillations are pervasive and may alleviate a proteome constraint&lt;/a&gt;. During my PhD, I also worked on a paper on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://arinwongprommoon.github.io/publication/nikoladosaccuracydataefficiency2022/&#34;&gt;accuracy and data efficiency in deep learning models of protein expression&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
